Academic Planning Services fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Academic Planning Services fonds
1972 - 1999
F-202
2.51 m of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of the records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by Simon Fraser University's Office of the Vice-President, Academic and Provost (October 2005).
Academic Planning Services
Academic Planning Services was established in September 1990 with the appointment of Alison Watt as the unit's first Director, reporting to the Vice-President, Academic (VPA). Academic Planning Services' main functions were to coordinate academic planning at the senior staff level, provide secretariat services to the Senate Committee on Academic Planning (SCAP), coordinate the process for external reviews of academic departments, oversee use of endowment funds to support academic programs, and maintain the university's policies and procedures manual.
In March 1996, Watt became Director, Secretariat Services, moving from the VPA's to the Registrar's portfolio and transferring a number of responsibilities with her. In subsequent years, academic planning support services have been variously organized through the VPA's Office. Kathy Heinrich was appointed Special Assistant to the VPA, Academic Planning in 1996 to assist academic restructuring processes; Heinrich left the university in the summer of 1999. A directorship for Academic Planning Services was re-established from 2000 to 2004 with the appointment of Sue Roppel (2000-2001), then Laurie Summers (2002-2004). In 2004, academic planning was reorganized with the creation of the Academic Planning and Budgeting Office, headed by Glynn Nichols as Director. This unit has a dual reporting relationship to both the VP Academic and the VP Finance and Administration through their respective Associate VPs.
published
Full
Published
The title of the fonds is based on the name of the creating body.
The fonds consists of records made or received or inherited by Academic Planning Services in the course of its activities. Activities documented include the operations of the the Academic Planning Committee (predecessor of the Senate Committee on Academic Planning), external reviews of university departments, new academic program proposals, and SFU's participation in TRIUMF (the particle accelerator facility located at the University of British Columbia and operated jointly by a number of Canadian universities). Records include meeting agendas, minutes and support papers, and external review reports and related documentation. For more detailed descriptions of record types, see individual series descriptions.
Note that many of the records were created before the establishment of Academic Planning Services and were inherited by the unit: all of series 1 (Academic Planning Committee), many files in series 2 (External reviews), all of series 3 (TRIUMF correspondence), and some of series 4 (General correspondence). Note also that the only records post-dating Alison Watt's tenure as Director (1990-1996) are found in series 2 (External reviews).
The material was arranged by the archivist based on groupings established by the creator. Series and sub-series are arranged chronologically by start date. Files within these groupings are arranged chronologically.
Office of the Vice-President, Academic and Provost
The records were transferred to the Archives in 1994 as a block of "Special project files" under Unscheduled Records Disposal (URD) 083-94. This transfer was part of a larger project the Archives undertook to appraise, schedule and dispose of records that had accumulated in the University Records Centre through the 1980s and early 1990s.
As of February 2006, all accessions have been processed. Future accruals may occur. The status of the records of Academic Planning Services' successor body (Academic Planning and Budget Office) has not yet been determined – i.e. if / when it transfers records to the Archives, whether these will be integrated into the present fonds or established as a new fonds.
A large number of the files contained in the fonds predate the formal establishment of Academic Planning Services. These records were either created earlier by Alison Watt, the first Director, in her previous position as Assistant to the Vice-President, Academic and carried forward into her new role; or the files were transferred to her for other reasons.
For the Vice-President, Academic's correspondence with the Director of Academic Planning Services, see fonds F-200 (Office of the Vice-President, Academic), series 2-17, Academic Planning / Secretariat Services (1992-1999).
The files of Kathy Heinrich as Special Assistant, Academic Planning are not included in this fonds, but were integrated by the creator into the VP Academic's record-keeping system; see fonds F-200 (Office of the Vice-President, Academic), series 2-20, Special Assistant to the Vice-President, Academic - Academic Planning (1995-2000).
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
A file list is available. Appendix A contains an index of access points (names) assigned to series.
- Academic Planning Committee files, 1972 - 1975; F-202-1; 25 cm of textual records; Academic Planning Committee
  The Academic Planning Committee (APC) was establsihed in 1970 as an advisory committee to the President and successor to the Senate's Long Range Academic Planning Committee. Its main functions were to review and recommend to the President, as Chair of Senate, all new program proposals submitted to it; and develop annually a recommendation to the President concerning academic and action priority listings. It was replaced in 1975 by the Senate Academic Planning Committee (SCAP).
  published
  This series consists of records relating to the activities and deliberations of the APC. The files were originally created by the Vice-President, Academic as a member of the committee. At some point in the early 1990s, the records were transferred to and integrated into the record-keeping system of Academic Planning Services. Activities and topics documented in the files include planning retreats at Harrison Hots Springs (May 31 - June 2 1972) and Westminster Abbey, Mission (December 11 - 13 1972); consideration of program proposals in the Fine Arts and in Communication; and the activities of an APC sub-committee relating to disputes in the Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology (PSA) department. Records include meeting agendas and minutes, correspondence, reports, and program proposals.
  Files are arranged chronologically.
  Academic Planning Committee; Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology
  No further accruals to the series are expected.
  For other records relating to the Academic Planning Committee, see:
  Fonds F-193, President's Office fonds. Series 28-3, Committees. Academic Planning Committee (1969-1980).
  Fonds F-109, School of Contemporary Arts fonds. Series 4-19, Committees. Academic Planning Committee (1969-1975).
  Fonds F-93, School of Computing Science. Series 3-29, Committees. Academic Planning Committee (1974-1976).
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  A file list is available.
  - APC retreat, vol. 1, June 1972; F-202-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - APC retreat, vol. 2, June 1972; F-202-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-1)
    Pending review
  - APC retreat, vol. 3, June 1972; F-202-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-1)
  - APC retreat, December 1974; F-202-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-1)
  - APC sub-committee (PSA Department split), vol. 1, 1973; F-202-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 202-1)
  - APC sub-committee (PSA Department split) - report, vol. 1, 1973; F-202-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 202-1)
  - APC sub-committee (PSA Department split) - report, vol. 2, 1973; F-202-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 202-1)
  - Communication Studies, 1972; F-202-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 202-2)
    Restricted in part
  - Fine and Performing Arts proposal, vol. 1, 1972 - 1975; F-202-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 202-2)
  - Fine and Performing Arts proposal, vol. 2, 1972 - 1975; F-202-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 202-2)
  - Fine and Performing Arts proposal, vol. 3, 1972 - 1975; F-202-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 202-2)
  - Fine and Performing Arts proposal, vol. 4, 1972 - 1975; F-202-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 202-2)
  - Fine and Performing Arts proposal - report and documents, 1972; F-202-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 202-2)
- External review files, 1972 - 1999; F-202-2; 1.89 m of textual records
  Senate policy requires that all academic departments undergo periodic external review. The Vice-President, Academic's Office has responsibility for coordinating this process, advising departments on timelines, assisting with the preliminary self-study, identifying potential external reviewers, and receiving and disseminating documentation. After 1990, these responsibilities were delegated to Academic Planning Services. Files relating to earlier reviews were transferred and integrated into the record-keeping system of Academic Planning Services.
  This series consists of records relating to the external review process. All the departments reviewed are academic units, with three exceptions: the Registrar (sub-series 7), the University Library (sub-series 14), and the Financial Aid and Awards Office (sub-series 18). Records include review check lists, correspondence, site visit schedules, departmental self-study reports, CVs, budgets, surveys, departmental handbooks and other printed matter, meeting minutes, external review reports, and departmental responses to the external review.
  Each department has been assigned its own sub-series, which brings together all reviews of that that department over time. Sub-series are generally arranged chronologically by start date. Files within sub-series are arranged chronologically.
  Further accruals to the series are expected.
  For other records relating to the external review process, see two series in the fonds of the Office of the Vice-President, Academic' (F-200):
  F-200-2-17-2, Academic Planning Services / Secretariat Services. External Reviews (1992-1999).
  F-200-8-3-34, University committees. External review committees (1990-1991).
  See also the faculty and departmental fonds of the units reviewed.
  A file list is avaiable.
  - External reviews - general files, 1972; F-202-2-1; 2 cm of textual records
    Faculty of Science
    - Faculty of Science external reviews - summary, 1972; F-202-2-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-3)
  - Department of Biology external review files, 1972 - 1989; F-202-2-2; 7 cm of textual records
    Department of Biological Sciences
    - Biological Sciences external review, vol. 1, 1972; F-202-2-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-3)
    - Biological Sciences external review, vol. 2, 1972; F-202-2-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-3)
    - Biological Sciences external review, vol. 1, 1988 - 1989; F-202-2-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-3)
    - Biological Sciences external review, vol. 2, 1988 - 1989; F-202-2-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-3)
  - Department of Mathematics and Statistics external review files, 1972 - 1990; F-202-2-3; 7 cm of textual records
    Department of Mathematics
    - Mathematics external review, vol. 1, 1972; F-202-2-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-3)
    - Mathematics external review, vol. 2, 1972; F-202-2-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-3)
    - Mathematics external review, vol. 3, 1972; F-202-2-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-4)
    - Mathematics external review, 1988 - 1990; F-202-2-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-4)
  - Department of Chemistry external review files, 1972 - 1994; F-202-2-4; 9 cm of textual records
    Department of Chemistry
    - Chemistry external review, vol. 1, 1972; F-202-2-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-4)
    - Chemistry external review, vol. 2, 1972; F-202-2-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-4)
    - Chemistry external review, vol. 1, 1987 - 1988; F-202-2-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-4)
    - Chemistry external review, vol. 2, 1987 - 1988; F-202-2-4-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-4)
    - Chemistry external review, vol. 1, 1993 - 1994; F-202-2-4-0-5 (Archival box - standard 202-4)
    - Chemistry external review, vol. 2, 1993 - 1994; F-202-2-4-0-6 (Archival box - standard 202-4)
  - Department of Physics external review files, 1972 - 1990; F-202-2-5; 3 cm of textual records
    Department of Physics
    - Physics external review, 1972; F-202-2-5-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-5)
    - Physics external review, 1990; F-202-2-5-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-5)
  - Department of Psychology external review files, 1973 - 1993; F-202-2-6; 9 cm of textual records
    Department of Psychology
    - Psychology external review, vol. 1, 1973 - 1974; F-202-2-6-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-5)
    - Psychology external review, vol. 2, 1973 - 1974; F-202-2-6-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-5)
    - Psychology external review, vol. 1, 1991 - 1993; F-202-2-6-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-5)
    - Psychology external review, vol. 2, 1991 - 1993; F-202-2-6-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-5)
    - Psychology external review, vol. 3, 1991 - 1993; F-202-2-6-0-5 (Archival box - standard 202-5)
    - Psychology external review, vol. 4, 1991 - 1993; F-202-2-6-0-6 (Archival box - standard 202-5)
  - Office of the Registrar external review files, 1974 - 1975; F-202-2-7; 8 cm of textual records
    Registrar's Office
    - Registrar external review, vol. 1, 1974 - 1975; F-202-2-7-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-6)
    - Registrar external review, vol. 2, 1974 - 1975; F-202-2-7-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-6)
    - Registrar external review, vol. 3, 1974 - 1975; F-202-2-7-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-6)
  - Department of English external review files, 1974 - 1987; F-202-2-8; 11 cm of textual records
    Department of English
    - English external review, vol. 1, 1974; F-202-2-8-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-6)
    - English external review, vol. 2, 1974; F-202-2-8-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-6)
    - English external review, vol. 3, 1974; F-202-2-8-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-7)
    - English external review, vol. 4, 1974; F-202-2-8-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-7)
    - English external review, 1987; F-202-2-8-0-5 (Archival box - standard 202-7)
  - Department of Geography external review files, 1974 - 1995; F-202-2-9; 17 cm of textual records
    Department of Geography
    - Geography external review, vol. 1, 1974 - 1975; F-202-2-9-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-7)
    - Geography external review, vol. 2, 1974 - 1975; F-202-2-9-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-7)
    - Geography external review, vol. 3, 1974 - 1975; F-202-2-9-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-7)
    - Geography external review, vol. 4, 1974 - 1975; F-202-2-9-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-8)
    - Geography external review, vol. 5, 1974 - 1975; F-202-2-9-0-5 (Archival box - standard 202-8)
    - Geography external review, vol. 6, 1974 - 1975; F-202-2-9-0-6 (Archival box - standard 202-8)
    - Geography external review, vol. 1, 1990 - 1995; F-202-2-9-0-7 (Archival box - standard 202-8)
    - Geography external review, vol. 2, 1990 - 1995; F-202-2-9-0-8 (Archival box - standard 202-8)
    - Geography external review, vol. 3, 1990 - 1995; F-202-2-9-0-9 (Archival box - standard 202-8)
  - Department of History external review files, 1974 - 1998; F-202-2-10; 11 cm of textual records
    Department of History
    - History external review, vol. 1, 1974; F-202-2-10-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-8)
    - History external review, vol. 2, 1974; F-202-2-10-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-9)
    - History external review, vol. 3, 1974; F-202-2-10-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-9)
    - History external review, vol. 1, 1993 - 1998; F-202-2-10-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-9)
    - History external review, vol. 2, 1993 - 1998; F-202-2-10-0-5 (Archival box - standard 202-9)
    - History external review, vol. 3, 1993 - 1998; F-202-2-10-0-6 (Archival box - standard 202-9)
    - History external review, vol. 4, 1993 - 1998; F-202-2-10-0-7 (Archival box - standard 202-9)
  - Department of Philosophy external review files, 1974 - 1998; F-202-2-11; 7 cm of textual records
    Department of Philosophy
    - Philosophy external review, vol. 1, 1974; F-202-2-11-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-9)
    - Philosophy external review, vol. 2, 1974; F-202-2-11-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-9)
    - Philosophy external review, vol. 1, 1993 - 1998; F-202-2-11-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-10)
    - Philosophy external review, vol. 2, 1993 - 1998; F-202-2-11-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-10)
  - Department of Economics external review files, 1975 - 1994; F-202-2-12; 10 cm of textual records
    Department of Economics
    - Economics and Commerce external review, vol. 1, 1975 - 1976; F-202-2-12-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-10)
    - Economics and Commerce external review, vol. 2, 1975 - 1976; F-202-2-12-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-10)
    - Economics and Commerce external review, vol. 3, 1975 - 1976; F-202-2-12-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-10)
    - Economics external review, vol. 1, 1992 - 1994; F-202-2-12-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-10)
    - Economics external review, vol. 2, 1992 - 1994; F-202-2-12-0-5 (Archival box - standard 202-10)
    - Economics external review, vol. 3, 1992 - 1994; F-202-2-12-0-6 (Archival box - standard 202-11)
  - School of Kinesiology external review files, 1976 - 1994; F-202-2-13; 8 cm of textual records
    Department of Biomedical Physiology and Kinesiology
    - Kinesiology external review, vol. 1, 1976; F-202-2-13-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-11)
    - Kinesiology external review, vol. 2, 1976; F-202-2-13-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-11)
    - Kinesiology external review, vol. 3, 1976; F-202-2-13-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-11)
    - Kinesiology external review, vol. 1, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-13-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-11)
    - Kinesiology external review, vol. 2, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-13-0-5 (Archival box - standard 202-11)
  - Simon Fraser University Library external review files, 1984 - 1993; F-202-2-14; 7 cm of textual records
    University Library
    - Library external review, 1984; F-202-2-14-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-11)
    - Library external review, vol. 1, 1990 - 1993; F-202-2-14-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-11)
    - Library external review, vol. 2, 1990 - 1993; F-202-2-14-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-12)
    - Library external review, vol. 3, 1990 - 1993; F-202-2-14-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-12)
    - Library external review, vol. 4, 1990 - 1993; F-202-2-14-0-5 (Archival box - standard 202-12)
  - School of Communication external review files, 1988 - 1994; F-202-2-15; 3 cm of textual records
    School of Communication
    - Communication external review, vol. 1, 1988 - 1994; F-202-2-15-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-12)
    - Communication external review, vol. 2, 1988 - 1994; F-202-2-15-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-12)
  - Continuing Studies external review files, 1989 - 1991; F-202-2-16; 3 cm of textual records
    Continuing Studies
    - Continuing Studies external review, vol. 1, 1989 - 1991; F-202-2-16-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-12)
    - Continuing Studies external review, vol. 2, 1989 - 1991; F-202-2-16-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-12)
  - Faculty of Business Administration external review files, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-17; 5 cm of textual records
    Beedie School of Business
    - Business Administration external review, vol. 1, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-17-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-12)
    - Business Administration external review, vol. 2, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-17-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-12)
    - Business Administration external review, vol. 3, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-17-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-13)
  - Financial Aid and Awards Office external review files, 1990 - 1991; F-202-2-18; 6 cm of textual records
    Financial Aid and Awards
    - Financial Aid and Awards external review, vol. 1, 1990 - 1991; F-202-2-18-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-13)
    - Financial Aid and Awards external review, vol. 2, 1990 - 1991; F-202-2-18-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-13)
    - Financial Aid and Awards external review, vol. 3, 1990 - 1991; F-202-2-18-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-13)
  - Department of Archaeology external review files, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-19; 8 cm of textual records
    Department of Archaeology
    - Archaeology external review, vol. 1, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-19-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-13)
    - Archaeology external review, vol. 2, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-19-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-13)
    - Archaeology external review, vol. 3, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-19-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-14)
    - Archaeology external review, vol. 4, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-19-0-4 (Archival box - standard 202-14)
  - Department of French external review files, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-20; 2 cm of textual records
    Department of French
    - French external review, 1990 - 1994; F-202-2-20-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-14)
  - Department of Political Science external review files, 1990 - 1995; F-202-2-21; 6 cm of textual records
    Department of Political Science
    - Poltical Science external review, vol. 1, 1990 - 1995; F-202-2-21-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-14)
    - Poltical Science external review, vol. 2, 1990 - 1995; F-202-2-21-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-14)
    - Poltical Science external review, vol. 3, 1990 - 1995; F-202-2-21-0-3 (Archival box - standard 202-14)
  - Faculty of Education external review files, 1991 - 1994; F-202-2-22; 4 cm of textual records
    Faculty of Education
    - Education external review, vol. 1, 1991 - 1994; F-202-2-22-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-15)
    - Education external review, vol. 2, 1991 - 1994; F-202-2-22-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-15)
  - Gerontology Program external review files, 1991 - 1994; F-202-2-23; 2 cm of textual records
    Gerontology Research Centre
    - Gerontology external review, 1991 - 1994; F-202-2-23-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-15)
  - School of Comptuing Science external review files, 1991 - 1995; F-202-2-24; 4 cm of textual records
    School of Computing Science
    - Computing Science external review, vol. 1, 1991 - 1995; F-202-2-24-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-15)
    - Computing Science external review, vol. 2, 1991 - 1995; F-202-2-24-0-2 (Archival box - standard 202-15)
  - Department of Linguistics external review files, 1991 - 1998; F-202-2-25; 2 cm of textual records
    Department of Linguistics
    - Linguistics external review, 1991 - 1998; F-202-2-25-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-15)
  - Cognitive Science Program external review files, 1993; F-202-2-26; 2 cm of textual records
    - Cognitive Science external review, 1993; F-202-2-26-0-1 (Archival box - standard 202-15)